<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A testimony of truth given forth by a servant of the Lord, on the behalf of the despised servants, and professors of truth, who are made partakers of the heavenly power, which shakes the earth, and makes the inhabitants of the land to tremble, who are by the scorners of this generation called Quakers against the many lyes and slanders which the devil is the chief author of, arising forth of the bottomlesse pit, and vented forth by one James Livesey a professed minister of Christ in the county of Chester, but by his fruits is plainly manifested a minister of sin, and so of his Father who begat him, and sent him forth to oppose the living truth of God : but his folly is here manifested and declared to open view, that the simple and honest hearted may turn from him and all such deceitful workers, and may learn of Christ the light of the world, that their souls may live.</title>
            <author>Parker, Alexander, 1628-1689.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 99 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A56109</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P386</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R5756</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12798270</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12798270</idno>
            <idno type="VID">94006</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A56109)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 94006)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 725:21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A testimony of truth given forth by a servant of the Lord, on the behalf of the despised servants, and professors of truth, who are made partakers of the heavenly power, which shakes the earth, and makes the inhabitants of the land to tremble, who are by the scorners of this generation called Quakers against the many lyes and slanders which the devil is the chief author of, arising forth of the bottomlesse pit, and vented forth by one James Livesey a professed minister of Christ in the county of Chester, but by his fruits is plainly manifested a minister of sin, and so of his Father who begat him, and sent him forth to oppose the living truth of God : but his folly is here manifested and declared to open view, that the simple and honest hearted may turn from him and all such deceitful workers, and may learn of Christ the light of the world, that their souls may live.</title>
                  <author>Parker, Alexander, 1628-1689.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>39 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Thomas Simmons ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed: "Given forth at Reading the latter end of the 4. Mon. 1659. A.P."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Livesey, James, 1625-1682.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Apologetic works.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:94006:1"/>
            <p>A TESTIMONY OF TRUTH, Given forth by a Servant of the Lord, on the behalf of the deſpiſed ſervants, and profeſſors of truth (who are made partakers of the heavenly Power, which ſhakes the earth, and makes the Inhabitants of the Land to tremble, who are by the ſcorners of this Generation called Quakers] againſt the many lyes and ſlanders (which the Devil is the chief author of) ariſing forth of the bottomleſſe pit, and vented forth by one <hi>James Liveſey</hi> a profeſſed Miniſter of Chriſt in the County of <hi>Cheſter;</hi> but by his fruits is plainly manifeſted a Miniſter of ſin, and ſo of his Father who begat him, and ſent him forth to oppoſe the living truth of God; but his folly is here manifeſted and declared to open view, that the ſimple and honeſt hearted may turn from him, and all ſuch deceitful workers, and may learn of Chriſt the light of the World, that their ſouls may live.</p>
            <q>Bleſſed are yee when men ſhall revile you, and perſecute you, and ſhall ſay all manner of evil againſt you falſly for my ſake; rejoyce and be exceeding glad, for great is your reward in Heaven, for ſo perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted they the Prophets which were before you, <bibl>
                  <hi>Mat. 5.11, 12.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>For as concerning this Sect we know that every where it is ſpoken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt, <bibl>
                  <hi>Acts 18.22</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>But this I confeſſe, that after the way which they call hereſie, ſo worſhip I the God of my Fathers, <bibl>
                  <hi>Acts 24.14.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>Truth was formerly called a Sect, and the way of God here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie by formal profeſſors; Therefore let none be deceived with vain words and flying reports. <q>But prove all things; and hold faſt that which is good, <bibl>1 Theſ. 5.21.</bibl>
               </q> 
               <bibl>
                  <hi>A. Parker.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Simmons</hi> at the <hi>Bull</hi> and <hi>Mouth</hi> near <hi>Alderſgate,</hi> 1659.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:94006:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:94006:2"/>
            <p>THe Almighty wiſe God, hath (according to his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe declared by his holy Prophets and Apoſtles ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared in theſe laſt dayes, and hath cauſed his light to ſhine forth, which hath not onely diſcovered and manifeſted the deceits of the ſerpent, and all the deceitful workers in all their deceivableneſſe, and cunning craftineſſe, whereby they have long lain in wait to deceive, and many have been deceived and led away from the light, which ſhould have given unto them the true knowledge of the Myſteries of God, and of thoſe things that doth pertain unto life and peace; I ſay the Lord our God hath not onely revealed the Myſtery of iniquity, but hath alſo (to the glory and praiſe of his great Name) revealed, and in a great meaſure diſcovered the myſtery of truth, which is glorious and precious, even that ſame Truth which (in ages and generations paſt) hath been the ſtay and comfort of Gods people, and was their joy and refreſhment, and did uphold them in the time of their tryals and troubles, which from the beginning of times ever ſince the fall of man, hath been gain-ſaid and oppoſed by the ſeed of evil doers, and thoſe who have from time to time born a true teſtimony for the truth (who lived in the truth) they have been reviled and reproached, and ſuffered many and great afflictions in the world, chiefly from thoſe who have had a name and an outward profeſſion of God, but lived out of the life of God; ſuch have been the enemies of God, and of his Truth, and alſo of his Meſſengers and ſervants, who have been true witneſſes of Truth (as the ſcriptures of Truth do largely teſtifie all along to which I refer thee that may read this, to ſearch and try) and as it was then in the dayes of old, even ſo it is now, he that is born after the fleſh doth perſecute him that is born after the ſpirit; and it cannot be otherwiſe, for there can be no agreement between light and darkneſſe, between Chriſt and Antichriſt; but enmity, and diſcord, war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and fighting one againſt the other, and ſo as we are made partakers according to our ſeveral meaſures of that life of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:94006:3"/>Righteouſneſſe which the Saints, the people of God were made partakers of, ſo we are made ſharers and partakers with them of the like ſufferings; and this we do account to be our joy and great riches, and do rejoyce in Chriſt that we are of that number who ſuffer for Righteouſneſſe ſake, well know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that according as it is written, all that will live godly in Jeſus Chriſt ſhall ſuffer perſecution.</p>
            <p>Now it being ſo that the moſt high God in his dear love in Chriſt Jeſus, having viſited this Nation with mercy from on high, even in a time when many were wallowing in their blood, and even paſt hope of recovery, the Nation being o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-run with wickedneſs, even then did God appear, and rent the thick vail, which had long been over many, and cauſed his light to ſhine out of obſcurity, and uttered forth his voyce in great power, and raiſed up many from the grave, and reſtored them to life again who had been dead in treſpaſſes and ſins, reviving them by his quickning power, and brought life and immortality to light through the Goſpel, and revealed the great myſteries of his Kingdom, which hath been hid from the worldly wiſe, even from the beginning of time, which is <hi>Chriſt in us the hope of glory,</hi> who was revealed and manifeſted in the true Chriſtians in the primitive times, This was their Priviledge, <hi>they were made partakers of life eternal, and tranſlated out of the kingdom of darknes, into the Kingdom of the Dear Son of God;</hi> they had the <hi>true light in them,</hi> &amp; the <hi>word of life was in them,</hi> by which they were ſanctified and made holy, <hi>and their bodies were Temples of God, and God and Chriſt dwelt in them and ſpake in them,</hi> and wrought all their works <hi>for them and in them;</hi> and ſo by the cords of pure love, they were drawn neer unto God, who ſometimes were afar off; and <hi>their uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty was in the ſpirit,</hi> for they <hi>were written in one anothers hearts, with the ſpirit of the living God;</hi> but ſince thoſe dayes, there hath been a great darkneſs over the Nations, and that Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian beauty of <hi>love, meekneſſe, patience, humility,</hi> &amp;c. hath been marred and ſtained by the deformed ſpots of <hi>envy, wrath, raſhneſſe, impatiency, pride, covetouſneſſe</hi> and the like; and though many have retained and kept the name of Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, yet the life and nature hath been wanting, as the true light hath made it manifeſt; for after theſe many years of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:94006:3"/>profeſſion, and theſe glorious and fair pretences, God is coming to view the fields, and to ſee what fruits may be reap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in this Nation, and Nations, and behold a great crop of corruption may be reaped, but no fruits from the good ground is brought forth, which hath grieved the good ſpirit of God; and now is he ariſen as a man of War in dread and fury, and will pour forth the Vialls of his wrath upon the man of Sin, and will bring deliverance, and hath brought deliverance unto his people, and this we teſtifie that <hi>God is light,</hi> and is appearing in the power <hi>of light</hi> to manifeſt and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy ſin, and bring in everlaſting righteouſneſs, and this is no new truth, but the ſame as ever, even that which was from the beginning, which is the ſame to day and for ever; and unto <hi>that</hi> which all people have erred from, is the Lord now bringing them back again <hi>unto,</hi> that they may have union with him <hi>in ſpirit,</hi> and worſhip him <hi>in ſpirit and in truth,</hi> and this is the worſhip that we own, and the true faith which is <hi>the gift of God,</hi> which we are made partakers of, which puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies the heart, and gives victory over the world, and the luſts and pollutions of it; and for this faith and no other, do we contend againſt all oppoſers and gainſayers (as many we have met withall within theſe few years, in this Nation of <hi>England</hi> ſince the glorious light of truth did ſhine forth) but over them all the truth doth reigne and ſhall reigne, and the Lamb ſhall have the victory; And amongſt the many oppoſers who have appeared by word and writing againſt the truth, I have lately ſeen a book given forth by one <hi>James Liveſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y,</hi> a Pariſh Prieſt in <hi>Cheſhire</hi> who hath vomited forth a great de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l of ſilthy ſtuff, like ſmoke from the bottomleſs pit, which darkens the aire, and blinds the eyes of ſome peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple there away, and cauſes them to ſtumble at the appearance of truth. Now for the truths ſake and for their ſakes who love it, I am made free to write ſome few things to the chief points or heads in the ſaid book, for the manifeſting and laying open deceit, and removing the ſtumbling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blocks out of the way of the ſimple; as for my own particular I am ſatisfied, and I know many more in this Nation, who have received of the fulneſs of God, and have drunk of the ſweet and pleaſant ſtreams that have ſprung from the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:94006:4"/>of <hi>Sion,</hi> and have received ſatisfaction, and can no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger drink of the dury, muddy, filthy ſtreams that ſprings from the well head of <hi>Babylon,</hi> nor can any longer trade with the deceitful Merchants of <hi>Babylon;</hi> for the day of her cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity is come, and the Lord is diſcovering the witchcraft and ſorcery of her Merchants, unto thouſands is this Nation, and other parts, who can buy her Merchandize no more; but to come to the matter in hand, and the firſt things I meet with in the Book aforeſaid in the firſt page, are ſome reliques or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainders of ſome old wares which this Merchant of <hi>Babylon</hi> hath taken back again from ſomething formerly ſold by him, which he caſts in to fill up the meaſure of the other, which he hath compacted together to make ſale of, which I may paſſe over and come to the matter, and its poſſible when the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandize is opened, I may find ſome of theſe reliques, and may return them back again with the other deceitful wares, unto this Merchant of <hi>Babylon,</hi> for the Children of <hi>Sion</hi> loaths them, and will no longer buy them.</p>
            <p>Pr. <hi>Is the written word Gods?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The written words or ſayings of the holy men of God, ſo far as they are not corrupted in the tranſlations, I own to be a true teſtimony or declaration of the eternal word, and being given forth from the moving of the ſpirit they are good, they are words of God, and dearly owned and prized by us, and were given forth to be read, believed, practiſed and fulfilled, but He cannot be written with pen or ink whoſe Name is called the word of God.</p>
            <p>Pr <hi>Then in the next place, what ever humane doctrines or opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons you meet with which thwart, contradict or oppoſe the written word; reject.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> We who fear God, and are led and guided by the ſpirit of God, which leadeth into all truth, we do not act things contradictory to the Scriptures, though to dark under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings, ſomething may be ſo judged, as ſometimes in the dayes paſt, the chief Prieſt and great profeſſors Judged the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters Chriſt, who denyed the outward commandments and ſhadows of the Law, which were commands of God written in the Scriptures, as the Temple, Sabbath, circumciſion, Prieſts, tythes, oſterings and the like, and brought people to the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:94006:4"/>guidings and leadings of the holy ſpirit, and the holy unction within them; but the Prieſts of <hi>England</hi> do act things inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by humane wiſdom, and that which doth oppoſe and contradict plain Scriptures: as firſt their carnal, and man-made Miniſtry, being brought up at Schools and Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, and ſo made Miniſters in and by the will of man, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to <hi>Paul</hi> who neither received it of man, neither was he taught it, but by the Revelation of Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>Gal</hi> 1.1.11.12.15.16. 2 Their man-made Churches which God never com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to be built in the Goſpel miniſtration; but on the contrary ſaid, <hi>God that made the World and all things therein, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he is Lord of Heaven and earth, dwelleth not in Temples made with hands, &amp;c.</hi> 3. Their carnal call by ringing of bells. 4. their ſtanding praying in the high places there, and being called of men Maſter, contrary to the plain words of Chriſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23. who ſaith unto his true Miniſters, <hi>be not ye called of men Maſter, &amp;c.</hi> 5. Their long prayers, and ſtudied Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons (as they call them) their ſinging of <hi>Davids</hi> experiences in Rhime and Meter, which they doth not witneſſe in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves nor hearers, their ſprinkling of Infants, an invention of man never commanded by Chriſt, nor practiſed by his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles; their yearly ſet and forced maintenance, and many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things are done and acted by the Prieſts of <hi>England,</hi> which doth contradict and oppoſe plain Scriptures, and they have no example for ſuch practices, but are humane inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and therefore we do deny them and turn from them, and teſtiſie againſt them, and know aſſuredly that God will over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn them.</p>
            <p>The next thing I meet with, is a ſaying of <hi>Auſtin,</hi> which the Prieſt brings, which makes nothing for his purpoſe, but is altogether againſt the end for which it is alleadged, for <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſpeaks there of the teachings of Chriſt, and labours to bring from the teachings of men, the words are theſe; <hi>nec tu me, nec ego te, ſed ambo Chriſtum, audi veritatem loquentum, audi Chriſtum dicentem,</hi> neither hear thou me, nor will I hear thee, but let both of us hear Chriſt, hear the truth ſpeaking, hear Chriſt teaching; the words are ſound and good, for all fleſh is to be ſilent, and Chriſt muſt ſpeak in male and female; Ye ſeek a proof of Chriſt ſpeaking in me ſaith <hi>Paul,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.3. And
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:94006:5"/>the anointing which ye have received of him abides in you ſaith <hi>John,</hi> and ye need not that any man teach you, but as the ſame anointing teacheth you, 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.27. which teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of Chriſt <hi>Auſtin</hi> in this place ſpeakes of, which this op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſer <hi>Liveſey</hi> would apply to the Scriptures without, and ſo pervert his words above mentioned; But the words of <hi>Auſtin</hi> do not bear ſuch a ſenſe as Chriſt ſpeaking in the Scripture, but hear Chriſts teaching, and ſo let him that hath an ear to hear, hear what the Spirit ſaith.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pr.</hi> Furthermore I find a Scripture quoted <hi>Iſay</hi> 8.20. <hi>To the Law, and to the Teſtimony,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> To which I ſay, the Law is light and was written in the heart, and the teſtimony of Jeſus is the ſpirit of propheſie, which ſpirit is a diſcerner and a tryer of Doctrines and opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; but that the Scriptures themſelves are the touchſtone and tryer without the ſpirit, I deny, &amp; I put it upon <hi>Liveſey</hi> (truths oppoſer) to prove; but to give a little light to the people who do not underſtand aright, this I ſay, that in tryal of things and ſpirits, there is three things to be conſidered of, that is, <hi>the tryer</hi> and the <hi>thing tryed,</hi> and the <hi>Rule to try by;</hi> Now if I grant the Scriptures to be a rule, yet a blind man cannot ſee them, nor walk according to them, ſo that whoſoever doth Judge of things, or go about to try ſpirits, if he have not the ſpirit of God in his own particular, he cannot try nor Judge aright, &amp; whereas he ſpeaks of conſcience being <hi>Regula regulata, non regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la regulans,</hi> I ſay the conſcience is not the rule, but the light, or ſpirit of God, which exerciſes the conſcience towards God &amp; man, that is the true rule; for as many as are the Sons of God they are led by the ſpirit of God;</p>
            <p>Pr. And whereas he further ſaith, <hi>It may not be unſeaſonable nor unprofitable to give you of this Congregation a ſhort draught of ſome opinions owned and maintained by the</hi> Quakers.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> To which I ſay &amp; in the fear of God I declare unto you who are hearers of the ſaid <hi>Liveſey,</hi> that to hear a lyar, and a falſe accuſer, is both unſeaſonable &amp; unprofitable; and hear him ſo long as you will, you ſhall never be profited by him nor con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted to God, for being out of the Counſel of God himſelf, he cannot bring others unto God; and that he is a lyer and a falſe accuſer, I ſhall make it plainly manifeſt, as I come to his charges
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:94006:5"/>againſt thoſe people; for I have read over his Book or Papers, and I find a great heap of filthy ſtuff; for wanting matter where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withall to accuſe, he himſelf layes a falſe foundation, and then goes to build, inventing lies and falſe things, and calls them the <hi>Quakers</hi> opinions; and ſo heaps a great deal of ſtuff together, and to colour his deceit, gathers up ſeveral texts of Scriptures, and makes a great noiſe, as though he had confuted the <hi>Quakers</hi> opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, when indeed it is nothing but his own lies and inventions that he hath confuted; like unto a diſtracted man, creating imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, and then fights with his own created images, as this oppoſer doth, as I ſhall make it manifeſt in due time; and ſo that which he caſts upon the <hi>Quakers,</hi> will juſtly fall upon his own head; for where envy, lying and falſe accuſing is, that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion is not of God; but (to turn back his own words) is a mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lany of froth, filth, vanity, and villanie, lies, and lewdneſs, errors, Hereſies and blaſphemies, which they have invented, and through covetouſneſs and love of money have deceived the Nations long with, which grieves the hearts of the righteous; but the Lord in due time will throw down <hi>Babylon,</hi> and mar all her Wars, and ſpoil all her Merchants, and the great Whore which hath made all Nations drunk with the cup of her fornication, ſhall be caſt upon a bed of ſorrow, and all who have committed whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom with her ſhall drink the cup of fury and indignation of God, and the Beaſt and falſe prophets which have deceived the Nations ſhall be caſt into a lake of fire burning with Brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone.</p>
            <p>But I ſhall be as ſhort as I may have liberty from the Lord, and come to his charges and accuſations againſt thoſe whom he calls <hi>Quakers,</hi> and the firſt is this.</p>
            <p>Pr. <hi>There is an opinion amongſt them that ſalvation is attainable without Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> That is a wicked lie, I deteſt and abhor that ſpirit that uttered forth thoſe words, there is no ſuch opinion among us, who are ſcornfully called <hi>Quakers;</hi> we profeſs ſalvation by Jeſus Chriſt, and not by any other thing or things; for of our ſelves we are not able to think a good thought, nor ſpeak a good word, nor do a good deed, but our ſtrength and ſufficiency is in Chriſts <hi>and Chriſt is in us the hope of our glory, and by him are we ſaved, and made free from the devils bondage and ſlavery,</hi> and from lying, and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:94006:6"/>ſlandering, and it it <hi>Chriſt in us</hi> that <hi>works our works,</hi> and enables us to perform and do his will; <hi>and we are Gods workmanſhip, Created in Chriſt Jeſus unto good works,</hi> and ſo I teſtifie that <hi>ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation is attainable in Christ,</hi> and not <hi>without him;</hi> and that lying ſpirit in Prieſt <hi>Liveſey</hi> I do deny; and this is his foundation upon which he builds; and the foundation being a lie, and rotten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, the building cannot ſtand; Gods vengeance and wrath is kindied, and all lyars and deceitful covetous hireling Prieſts ſhall be as ſtubble before the fire, and the Lake is the lyars portion, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.8. as for the Soriptures mentioned by him I own them in their place, and they ſtand a teſtimony againſt the lyar, and falſe acculer, and ſuch denies Chriſt, though in words they profeſſe him; ſo let every one who hears or read theſe lines ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine your ſelves whether or no you be in Chriſt, and Chriſt be in you, <hi>for except Jeſus Chriſt be in you ye are Reprobates,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.5.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pr. There is an opinion amongst them that the Scripture is not the word of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Scriptures of <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets, Chriſt, and the Apoſtles, are words of God, a Declaration of the things of God, and they teſtifie of Him whoſe Name is balled the Word God, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.13.</p>
            <p>Pr. <hi>There is an opinion among them that every man coming into the world hath in him, and connatural to him a ſaving light.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> As this is laid down it is falſe, invented in a falſe deceitful deceived heart, manifeſting his wickedneſs that gave it ſorth; But for the ſatisfaction of the upright I ſhall declare the truth, and that is this, we ſay that Jeſus Chriſt is the light of the world, and ſo it is written in the Scripture, <hi>Joh.</hi> 8 12. and he lighteth every man that cometh into the world, according to to the teſtimony of <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.9. and though darkneſs may be over the Nations, yet light ſhineth in darkneſs, but the darkneſs doth not comprchend the light, and this light is a manifeſtation of the fathers love in Jeſus Chriſt, and is Gods true and faithful witneſs, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proves in ſecret for ſin and evil, and doth make it mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt in the heart and conſcience, and reproves him or her that acts and commits it, and that which reproves and makes ſin manifeſt is light, as it is written, <hi>all things that are reproved are made manifeſt by the light, for whatſoever makes manifest is light,</hi> Epheſ. 5.13. this light is the key that opens the door where the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:94006:6"/>heavenly treaſure is, and no man or woman in the world can ever come to the true knowledge of ſin, much leſſe to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of truth in its purity, until they own the light which Jeſus Chriſt the light of the world hath enlightened them withal, thou canſt never ſee thy ugly ſhape and thy foul and filthy garments which the devil hath put upon thee; until thou vieweſt thy ſelf in this light; therefore beware of hating and deſpiſing the light within which is of Chriſt, for whoſoever hates that light which checks and reproves for ſin, they hate Chriſt, and the light is the condemnation; for as Chriſt hath ſaid, this is the condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the world, that light is come into the world, and men love darkneſs rather then light, becauſe their deeds be evil, for every one that doth truth, he loveth the light and brings his deeds to the light that they may be proved and tryed whether or no they be wrought in God, but every one that doth evil, hateth the light, and will not bring his deeds to the light, leaſt they ſhould be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved, <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pr. There is an opinion amongst them that every man may be ſaved if he will,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> This is likewiſe falſe, and no truth in it, for we do not ſay that the power of ſalvation is in mans will, but in God, who by his power ſubdues and ſubjects mans will; for it is not in him that willeth or runneth, but in God that ſhewes mercy, and this is the mercy and loving kindneſs of God who hath ſent his Son into the world, that whoſoever believeth on him ſhould not periſh but have everlaſting life; and ſo ſalvation is of God, but deſtruction is of a mans ſelf, for the grace of God that brings ſalvation hath appeared unto all men, teaching us, &amp;c. So he that will be a Diſciple of Chriſt muſt deny himſelf and take up his Croſſe and follow Chriſt, and the Croſſe of Chriſt crucifies the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal mind and ſubjects mans will and God worketh in the creature both to will and to do, yet obedience is required of the creature, that as God by his light doth ſhew his will and mind; it is the duty of men &amp; women to do his will which is our Sanctification.</p>
            <p>Pr. <hi>There is an opinion among them that there is in man no light of reaſon, no light of nature.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> All men that be out of the true light of life, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all that which they may call light of reaſon on light of nature, are darkneſs according to that Scripture, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.8. <hi>once
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:94006:7"/>were you darkneſs,</hi> &amp;c. and yet in that ſtate there is a ſpark or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome glimering of the true light which ſhines in darkneſs, but the darkneſs cannot comprehend it, <hi>Joh.</hi> 1. and this light is the ground of right reaſon, and men that deſpiſe and reject the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel of the light become brutiſh, and unreaſonable, and ſo the underſtanding comes to be darkened, and the ſence of it is loſt.</p>
            <p>Pr. <hi>There is an opinion that conſcience in man is nothing elſe but faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> That is not ſo; for conſcience in man may erre, and may be ſeared; but faith is pure, it is the gift of God, and cannot erre, and the myſtery of it is held in a pure conſcience.</p>
            <p>Pr. <hi>There is an opinion among them that the light within them is ſufficient, that there is no need of other teachers,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> That light that is of Chriſt, in it ſelf is ſufficient, but there be ſome that are but Babes and ſucklings, and the Lord takes care for them, and for this end was the true Miniſtry given, having received <hi>perfect gifts which were for the perfecting of the body of Chriſt, until all come into the unity of the faith, and of the knowledge of the Son of God, unto a perfect man, even to the meaſure and ſtature and fulneſs of Chriſt,</hi> and this doth not overthrow all Scripture, but eſtabliſh the Scriptures, for this is the very end for which the Scriptures, were given forth, to wit, that people may be brought to God, and worſhip God in ſpirit and in truth, and know the holy unction within them; and <hi>John</hi> did not overthrow the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures nor the true Miniſtry when he ſaid, <hi>the anointing which ye have received of him abides in you, and ye need not that any man teach you, but as the ſame anointing teacheth you,</hi> &amp;c. and the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> did not lay waſte the Scriptures, nor fruſtarte the work of the Miniſtry, when he ſaith, <hi>ceaſe from man whoſe breath is in his nosirils, for wherein is he to be accounted of?</hi> and as then the work of the true Prophets, and Apoſtles was to bring to God, ſo now, for <hi>all the children of the Lord ſhall be taught of the Lord,</hi> Iſai. 54.13.</p>
            <p>Pr. <hi>Their opinion is, that God is not to be worſhipped in places made with mens hands.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> We ſay, <hi>God is a ſpirit, and is worſhipped in Spirit, and in Truth, in his own holy Temple not made with mens hands;</hi> for <hi>God who made the world and all things therein, ſeeing he is Lord of heaven and Earth, dwelleth not in temples made with hands, neither is he worſhiped
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:94006:7"/>with mens hands,</hi> and this is truth, and whereas he the ſaid oppo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſer doth bring ſome ſcriptures, as <hi>Act.</hi> 20.7, 8, 9. how <hi>Paul</hi> preached in an upper chamber, and continued his ſpeech till midnight, this proves nothing for, but againſt him; for we bear witneſſe with the Apoſtle againſt the Temples made with hands, that God is not worſhipped there; and ſo as the Apoſtles did meet together apart from the Temple worſhippers, ſo do we now, and <hi>worſhip God in ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit;</hi> and whereas he brings ſome other Scriptures, as <hi>Luke</hi> 4.15. where Chriſt taught in the Synagogue, and <hi>Io.</hi> 18, 19, 20. which we deny not; but this was a time befroe he was ſacrificied up, and he came to fulfill all righteouſneſſe; for he is the end of the Law for Righteouſneſſe ſake to them that do believe; and whereas he adds a ſcripture in <hi>Pſa.</hi> 132.13, 14. For the Lord hath choſen <hi>Sion,</hi> he hath deſired it for his habitation, this is my reſt for ever, this he brings to prove that God is worſhipped, and dwels in a mans made houſe, if any be ſo blind and ignorant to believe him; for my part I believe him not; but I believe what the Scripture ſaith, <hi>Heaven is my Throne and earth is my footſtool, what houſe will you build unto me ſaith the Lord?</hi> or where is the place of my reſt? not in a man made houſe. The heaven of heavens is not able to contain him whom we worſhip.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pr. There is an opinion among them, that the place where the people of God convene to worſhip, is not the Church, nor to be called a Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> We ſay no, For the Church is the body of Chriſt built up of living ſtones, elect and precious, and the Apoſtle doth not any where call a man-made houſe a Church, and it is error and bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſphemie to call a houſe (made with mens hands of wood and dead ſtones) a Church; and therefore a vain wicked and ſottiſh aſſertion of this blind Prieſt ſo to call it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pr. There is an opinion among them; that God is not to be worſhiped in places where idolatrous worſhip hath been performed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> As for the daies of old, what was done then, we let paſſe, but as for your ſteeple-houſes which a few yeares ſince were the <hi>Popes</hi> Maſſe-houſes, God doth not dwell, neither is he rightly worſhipped there, and therefore we do denie them and all your dead performances in them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pr. There is an opinon among them that God is not worſhipped with the body.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:94006:8"/>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> God is worſhipped in ſpirit and ſerved with the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, according to that Scripture quoted by this oppoſer, Rom. 12. 1. <hi>I boſeech you therefore brethren by the mercies of God, that you pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent your bodies a living ſacrifice, Holy and acceptable unto God, which is your reaſonable ſervice,</hi> (mark he calls it a ſervice.)</p>
            <p>Pr. <hi>There is an opinion amongſt them that the law is made hy the beaſt, and it is not lawfull to uſe the law.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> The law which is perfect was made by God, <hi>and is good, juſt, and holy;</hi> and is for the lawleſſe to be as a curb and limit to them, which law we own, and all juſt lawes made by men, which are according to the law of God, we own; and therefore do I teſtifie againſt Prieſt <hi>Liveſey</hi> as a liar and falſe accuſer of the Innocent; as for all lawes that are unjuſt and contrary to the law of God, ſuch are made by the power of the beaſt, and ſuch lawes we cannot obey but teſtifie againſt them.</p>
            <p>Pr. <hi>There is an opinion amongſt them that there is no mediate call to the Miniſtry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> The true Miniſters of Chriſt their call was immediate, by the power and ſpirit of the living God, that which is mediate is carnal; and Chriſt is the ſame yeſterday, to day and for ever, and his call to the miniſtrie is immediate by his power and ſpirit, and all ſuch as denie an immediate call now, I denie them, they are not Miniſters of Chriſt, but of Antichriſt.</p>
            <p>Pr. <hi>There is an opinion amongst them, that Chriſt is the original language of truth, not</hi> Greek, <hi>not</hi> Hebrew.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> As this is laid down Iown it not, but this I ſay, that Chriſt is the fountain and fulneſſe and the original of all Truth, and the wiſeſt linguiſt in all the world, <hi>Grecian</hi> or <hi>Hebrewcian,</hi> cannot by all their skill open the door; nor ſuck any ſweetneſſe from this fountain, for it is locked and ſealed up, and only they that drink at the ſtream, the true light, do taſt of the ſweetneſſe, and ſuch receive ſatisfaction and refreſhment, and are led to the fountain, there to drink deep and full draughts, to their comfort and conſolation<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p>Pr. <hi>There is an opinion amongſt them that the conſcience of one man is the light of Chriſt in an other man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> This is altogether falſe and a lying invention of his own, and therefore I need not ſpeak to any thing in this charge, for the foundation being taken away, the building will quickly fall down to the ground.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:94006:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>Pr. <hi>There is an opinion amongst them that baptiſm of Infants is of the</hi> Popes <hi>institution.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Hath this oppoſer ſo long been trained up in the <hi>Popes</hi> way and order, and ſo long continued in the <hi>Popes</hi> Maſſe-houſe and hath he not yet learned all his inſtitutions? let him go to ſchool again, and he may find it among ſome of the old rotten traſh.</p>
            <p>But ſaith this oppoſor, this opinion is contrarie to <hi>Mat.</hi> 28 19, 20. <hi>Go and diſciple all nations baptiſing them,</hi> were there no infants in all the world, nor in all the nations ſaith he?</p>
            <p>I anſwer, This command of Chriſt doth not at all give power to ſprinkle infants, for they are not capable of diſcipling or teaching; mark that, <hi>go and diſciple all, nations baptiſing them,</hi> here is diſcipling before baptiſing, but children are not capable of being diſcipled, ſo not of being baptized with water, and ſo in this he contradicts himſelfe; beſides it is a thing never comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded nor practiſed by Chriſt nor anie that he ſent forth; and ſo to <hi>Rome</hi> he muſt go and ſeek the inſtitution of it, for the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures mentions no ſuch thing as ſprinkling of Infants, Chriſt ſaid ſuffer little children to come unto me, and forbid them not, for of ſuch is the Kingdome of God; he took them in his Armes and bleſſed them, but he did not ſprinkle water on their faces, as the Prieſts of <hi>England</hi> do; he ſets them as a figure, and ſaith whoſoever ſhall not receive the kingdome of God as a little child, ſhall not enter there in.</p>
            <p>Pr. <hi>There is an opinion among them; that they cannot ſin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Anſ. <hi>Whoſoever is born of God doth not commit ſin, for his ſeed re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines in him, and he cannot ſin becauſe he is borne of God,</hi> 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.9. But he that is born of the fleſh doth ſin altogether; and ſo if any man ſay he hath no ſin before the birth immortal be born in him, he doth deceive himſelfe, and the truth is not in him; but whoſoever doth own the light of Chriſt, that doth make mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt ſin, and confeſſe and forſake ſin, they ſhall find meroy; and <hi>walkingin the light, the blood of Chriſt cleanſeth from all ſin;</hi> and ſaid <hi>Iohn</hi> heſe things I write unto you, that you ſin not; <hi>Iohn</hi> doth make clear diſtinction between the two births the one from beneath, the other from above, <hi>whoſoever abides in Chriſt doth not ſin, whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſinneth hath not ſeen him nor known him, &amp;c.</hi> And whereas he mentions an other Scripture, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 7.20. <hi>that,</hi> with many other Scriptures, are ſpoken to the ſeed of the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> and not to
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:94006:9"/>the regenerate ſeed, <hi>for as it is written, he that is born of God ſinneth not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pr. There is an opinion amongſt them, that men are not now out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly to expreſſe their thankefulneſſe in a vocal ſolemn forme of bleſſing for what creature comforts they receive from the hand of God,</hi> exempli gratia, <hi>not to crave a bleſſing upon their meat.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> This is falſe and a lie, proceeding from the old root; for we do own and practiſe prayer by ſpeaking of words as the Lord by his ſpirit doth move, and owneth the ſaying of the Apoſtle where he ſaith, I will that men pray every where, lifting holy hands without wrath and doubting, ſuch their prayers are accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table unto God; but all lying covetous greedy men, who harbour wrath and malice in them, the Lord abhors, and loathes their ſervices; furthermore I ſay, that whoſoever doth ſee with a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle eye, doth ſee every creature of God to be good, and are ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſied by the word, and ſo to the pure all things are pure, and if ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver a word were ſpoken to the hearing of the eare, yet the bleſſing and vertue is felt in the creatures, and praiſes ariſes, and is given to God for his mircies who is over all, bleſſed for ever.</p>
            <p>Pr. <hi>There is an opinion amongſt them that ſalutations are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> This is falſe and untrue as others before mentioned, for ſalutations of love we own and practice, according to Scriptures, and what Chriſt ſaid and commanded as to that we practice, if we go into a houſe, we ſalute the houſe, and if the Son of peace be there, our peace remaines, but if not, it returns back to us again and we ſhake off the duſt of our feet as a teſtimony againſt ſuch who reject the love of God; and theſe ſalutaions we own in the fear of God, according to the Scriptures; but as for all the vain traditional cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes of the world, the capping, bowing, cringing and the like we deny, and all vain cuſtomarie words, which feeds the wrong part, we denie and ſpeak in the fear of God, as we are moved of God by his ſpirit; as for other things in this particular, the ground being taken away, the reſt will wither; as for the ſcriptures men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned I own in the true meaning of them, and in their places ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the mind of the ſpirit.</p>
            <p>Pr. <hi>There is an opinion amongst them, that Ordinances are not now in force, we are to wait for immediate inſpirations, and Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:94006:9"/>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> All the Ordinances and traditions of men, which have been invented and ſet up in the time of darkneſſe and night of Apoſtacie ſince the daies of the Apoſtles, which be carnal and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, we do deny; but all the pure, holy and ſubſtantial ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Chriſt which abides and endures for ever, we do own and practice, as the pure ſpirit of God doth move and lead us; and as for inſpirations and Revelations, firſt for inſpirations, this I ſay, that no man upon earth can know God, ſavingly in any other man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, then by the inſpiration of the holy ſpirit, <hi>for the things of God knowes noman but the ſpirit of God, and no man knowes the Son ſave the Father, neither knowes any man the Father but the Son, and he to whom ſoever the Son will reveal him;</hi> he that denyes Revelation, denies the knowledge of God.</p>
            <p>Pr. <hi>Faith came by hearing,</hi> Rom. 10.14. <hi>Now hear and your ſouls ſhall live ſo the promiſe runs,</hi> Iſai. 55.3. <hi>Now they ſay your ſouls may live though you never hear.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Its true, that faith comes by hearing, and hearing by the word of God; but where is the word to be found? read the 6.7. and 8. verſes of the tenth Chapter to the <hi>Romans,</hi> where the Apoſtle ſpeakes of the word of faith; <hi>Say not in thy heart who ſhall aſcend into heaven (that is to bring Chriſt down from above) or who ſhall deſcend into the deep, that is to bring up Christ againe from the dead, but what ſaith it? the word is nigh thee, even is thy mouth, and in thy heart, that is the word of faith that we preach.</hi> This was the word that faith came by the hearing of it, and this word was manifeſted in the Prophet, who ſaith <hi>come unto me, hear and your ſouls ſhall live;</hi> now whereas this oppoſer ſaith, that we ſay ſouls may live though they never hear; that is falſe, we do not ſay ſo, but exhort people to hearken to the voice of Chriſt, that their ſouls may live, and whoſoever hears Chriſt, (though they never hear a covetous proud prieſt more, who loves money, and ſeeks gain from his quarter; yet) their ſouls ſhall live; for ſuch as loves mony and are envious and proud, lyars and falſe accuſers, were never ſent of God, and ſhall never profit people at all; ſuch are to be turned away from; and whereas this oppoſer <hi>Liveſey</hi> ſpeaks againſt Revelations, and ſaies, <hi>What need have we to waite for Revelations?</hi> &amp;c. I ſay there is not any man that rightly knowes God, nor any thing of God but by Revelation; for though the Scriptures are given forth, and any one may buy them for mony,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:94006:10"/>yet none in all the world, no not the wiſeſt, nor the moſt learned of men can underſtand them, except the ſame ſpirit that gave them forth do reveal and open them; <hi>For as I have ſaid the things of God, knowes no man but the ſpirit of God:</hi> And whereas he que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and ſaith, Where hath theſe men a promiſe to incourage them thus to waite, &amp;c I ſay many and pretious are the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes and the reward of thoſe that wait upon the Lord, <hi>for be that waits upon the Lord, his ſtrength ſhall be renewed,</hi> and again, <hi>wait up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Lord, and he will ſave thee, there were never any that waited on the Lord in vain</hi> So I ſay, <hi>bleſſed are they that wait upon the Lord, and stand upon their watch and are not weary, the Lord will reward them with his everlaſting bleſſings, and give them an inheritance amongst the Saints in light.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Pr. <hi>The great object of the</hi> Quakers <hi>is grounded on the firſt of</hi> Ioh. 2.27. <hi>Ye need not that any man teach; this makes not for them nor their Revelations, but againſt both; See verſe foregoing, which ſpeaks of Sedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers,</hi> Iohn <hi>meanes as is evident, that they need not any of thoſe Sedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers to teach them but the ſpirit and the written word, and the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Chriſt were ſufficient.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> O the wickedneſſe of man! when once turned from the holy unction and light of the ſpirit within, how he twines and turnes, and confounds himſelfe as this oppoſer doth, one while accuſes the <hi>Quakers</hi> with denyal or ſlighting of the Scriptures, and here ſaith their great object is grounded on 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 2.27, what, neither be contented to let us own nor diſown? and then like his Maſter brings part of the ſcripture, and gives a wrong ſenſe of the other part; <hi>Ye need not that any man teach,</hi> ſaith ye, but the Scripture ſaith thus, <hi>but the annointing which ye have received of him, abideth in you; and ye need not that any man teach you, but as the ſame anointing teacheth, you of all things which is truth, and is no lye, and even as it hath taught you, ye ſhall abide in him;</hi> Here its plainly manifeſt, <hi>Iohn</hi> ſpeakes of the holy unction which taught them of all things, and labours to keep the Saints to the annoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting within them, as a ſafty againſt all Seducers and deceivers, who laboured to draw from it to their own inventions. And this ſame holy anointing we have received of God, to be our teacher &amp; we do deny and turne from all ſuch Seducers and lyars as <hi>James Liveſey,</hi> for ſuch are not of God, neither can enter into the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:94006:10"/>Pr. <hi>There is an opinion amongſt them, that no reverence is to be ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, no honour nor titles of honour to be given to man, Magistrate or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> The day of Gods mighty power is come, and the Lord is ſtaining the pride and the glory of all fleſh, and the everlaſting Goſple is preached, <hi>fear God and give glory to him, for the hour of his judgement is come, Jeſus Christ is our Captain, and we follow him that did not reſpect the perſons of men, neither received honour from men, who ſaith, how can ye believe that receive honour one of an other, and ſeeks not the honour that comes from God onely?</hi> we are ſuch as do not ſeek honour, nor receive honour from men, and this was the Chriſtians practice, which we own, but in the Lord we honour all men and give that which is juſt and due unto men, honour to whom ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, cuſtome to whom cuſtome; but amongſt the Saints there was no ſuch cuſtome as to Lord one over another; that was the manner of the heathens, but ſaith Chriſt, <hi>it ſhall not be ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Pr. <hi>There is an opinion amongſt them that its unlawful for Miniſters to take hire, any reward or encouragement for their preaching, not Tythes eſpecially.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> To preach for hire, Lucre or gain is a great evil, teſtified againſt, not onely in the old time under the Law by Gods true Prophets, but alſo by Chriſt and his Apoſtles; whatſoever was allowed by God, was free under the Law, as well as under the Goſpel, and when any did it for hire or gain, it was a loathſome and a filthy thing. When Tythes were allowed by the Law of God unto the tribe of <hi>Levie,</hi> they having no other portion or inheritance, it was a free thing, they people were to offer freely, and to bring their Tythes into the ſtore-houſe, and the Prieſts, which were ordained to offer burnt offerings and Sacrifices were to do it freely, a figure of Jeſus Chriſts laying down his body free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; and in thoſe daies when any did it for hire or gain, the Lord ſent his holy Prophets to teſtifie againſt them, as ye may read in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 56.10, 11. <hi>Jer.</hi> 5.30, 31. <hi>Mica</hi> 3.5.11. <hi>Eze.</hi> 34. <hi>chap. Hoſ.</hi> 6.9. and many others: And when Chriſt was come in the fleſh he changed the miniſtry, and alſo the maintenance, and gave forth new commiſſions; though he owned the Law (with all its commands and ordinances) in its place; and whereas he reproves the Phariſees, ſaying, Wo unto you Scribes and Phariſees, hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:94006:11"/>for you pay Tythe of Mint, Annis, and Cummin, and have omitted the weightier matters of the Law, judgement, mercy and faith, theſe ought you to <hi>have</hi> done, and not to leave the other undone; And upon theſe ſayings of Chriſt, this oppoſer <hi>Liveſey</hi> ſeemeth to be much ſtrengthened in upholding this great Idol of Tythes; ſaith he, Were not thoſe times in which thoſe Scribes and Phariſees were, the times of the Goſpel? are they reproved for pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Tythes, no, no? (ſaith he) theſe things ought you to have done ſaith Chriſt; theſe things ought not to have been done ſaith the <hi>Quakers.</hi> Anſ. Can a <hi>Leopard</hi> change his ſpots? or can this wicked Prieſt leave off his lying? When did any <hi>Quaker</hi> ſay that Tythes ought not to have been paid? I leave this as a charge and and weight upon the head of this oppoſer, and ſurely it will ſinke him into the pit at laſt, if he do not with ſpeed repent; but to clear the caſe, That was a time before that, Jeſus Chriſt was ſacrificed up, and he did not come to break, but to fulfill the Law; and therefore ſaith Chriſt, and ſo ſay we, <hi>Theſe things you ought to have done</hi> (mark a time perfectly paſt) he doth not ſay theſe things ye ought to do or continue; but ſpeaking to them who were under the Law, and not to the Goſpel Miniſters whom he ſent forth; For this was their commiſſion, freely ye have received, freely give; and into what City or Country ye come, enquire who is worthy (mark) he doth not ſay enquire what ſums of money people will give you for preaching, or what Tythes or Gleab Lands, or augmentations belongs to ſuch a place, that was abhorred by them (but they were to enquire) who was ſeeking the kingdom of God, and if any one was found wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy, and did receive them and hear their words, they were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed to ſtay and abide there, and they might freely eat and drink ſuch things as were ſet before them; <hi>For the worke-man is worthy of his meat,</hi> but if any did reject their ſayings and did not hear their words, <hi>they were to depart and ſhake off the duſt of their feet as a testimony against them,</hi> read <hi>Mat.</hi> 10. <hi>Luke</hi> 10. Here was a free Miniſtry and a free m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>intenance; agreeable to this, is that of the Apoſtle to the <hi>Corinthians</hi> 1 <hi>Epiſtle</hi> 9. <hi>chap.</hi> where he pleads his power and authority to cat and to drink with ſuch as did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive his teſtimony, which ſcriptures are much abuſed by the earthly covetous teachers in theſe daies, perverting the ſcriptures for their own ſelfiſh ends. The words of the Apoſtle are theſe, <hi>Have we not power to eat and to Drink?</hi> (mark) he doth not ſay,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:94006:11"/>have not we power to take Tythes, or 2. or 300 l. or more or leſſe by the year, but he ſhewes his power amongſt them, that he had power to forbear working, and ſo brings ſeveral ſimilitudes) <hi>who goeth a warfare at any time at his own charges? who planteth a vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard and eateth not of the fruit thereof? or who feedeth a flock and ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth not of the milk of the flock?</hi> (mark, it was cating where they had planted, and ſo he goes on) it is written in the Law, <hi>thou ſhalt not muzel the mouth of the Oxe that treadeth out the corne,</hi> and ſo ſay we, it were unjuſt to let the Oxe ſtarve that treads out corne; but there be ſome filthy beaſts that ſpoile the corne, and ſuch their mouthes muſt be ſtopped; but what are all theſe ſayings to the idle ſlothful teachers in our age? when do they go and plant a vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard, or get a flock, or tread out corne? when do they goe into other Nations to convert the Turks and heathens? they are ready to plead for the maintenance of Goſpel Miniſters, but why do they not do their work; the Apoſtles and Miniſters of Chriſt travelled up and down in hard labors and great ſufferings, and their great care was to make the Goſpel without charge; but the Teachers in <hi>England</hi> they love their fat benefices; and large houſes, and love not to go into the Lords battel, but if a larger benefice happen to be vacant, they be ready to go thither, that i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, from a little one to a great one; but I ſeldom ſee a Prieſt, or have known any to be moved or called from a fat benefice to a poor one; and ſo are contrary to the Goſpel Miniſters, who were or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained of Chriſt, and ſo have no right to their maintenance; they that preach the Goſpel may live of the Goſpel, and ſuch as ſow ſpirituall things may reap of the carnal things, what is neceſſary for his body for food and raiment, and this is allowable; and he that is taught in the word ought to communicate to him that teacheth in all good things freely, but not by conſtraint; but ſaith this oppoſer who minds earthly things, whoſe God is his bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Let him communicate in all his goods, hay, hemp, flax, pige, geeſe: I ſay the Miniſters of Chriſt did never plead ſo for their bellies; and as for Tythes, it was never paid amongſt the true Chriſtians, but the Miniſter of the Goſpel in the ſeventh chap. to the <hi>Hebrews</hi> ſpeaking through all the figures, Tythes before the Law, to <hi>Melchiſedeck</hi> the ſimilitude like the Son of God, Tythes under the Law to the Levitical Prieſthood, and ſpeakes of the change of the Prieſthood, and of the Law, and diſannulling the Commandement; and in the beginning of the eight chapter ſums
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:94006:12"/>up all in one, now ſaith he of the things that we have ſpokn of (and Tythes was one of the things) this is the ſum, Jeſus Chriſt, who is a Prieſt for ever, not after the order of <hi>Aaron,</hi> but by the power of an endleſs life, who is the end of all likeneſſes, the ſum of the ſignres, Types and ſhadowes, the end of the firſt Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood that received Tythes, and the end of the Law, and ſo an end of Tythes, and all who take or pay Tythes now, it is a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying of Chriſt to be come in the fleſh, and ſuch are Antichriſtian; and all Lawes and Statutes which are made by men for the pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Tythes God will overturn and throw down, and the true Chriſtians who are ſubject to the Ordinances and commands of Chriſt cannot obey, but teſtifie againſt ſuch Lawes which have been made in the dark times of Popery, which the Prieſts of <hi>England,</hi> who deny the Pope in words yet are upholden and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by his maintenance, which never any of the true Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Chriſt did, as this oppoſer doth in words confeſs that the Apoſtles took no Tythes; but I ſhall leave this point and go on, and leave Tythes and all ſet and forced maintenance to fall with the hireling and carnal-man-made Miniſters.</p>
            <p>And whereas this oppoſer and gain-ſayer is ſpeaking of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounding, adding and giving meanings upon the Scriptures, and brings the expounders of the Law, and <hi>Paul</hi> confounded the <hi>Jewes</hi> and the like, and then numbers himſelf amongſt them, and ſaith we are Chriſts Ambaſſadours, when he is manifeſted to be a lyar, a falſe accuſer, Preaching for hire, and is one in nature with thoſe blaſphemers who ſaid they were <hi>Jewes</hi> but were not, as theſe ſay they are Miniſters of Chriſt, but are not, but are the Synagogue of Satan.</p>
            <p>Pr. <hi>There is an opinion amongst them that the Church of England is no true Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> That which is commonly called the Church, which this oppoſer went about to prove, to wit, a place built with mens hands, is no true Church, neither are the Saints that meets in thoſe Idolatrous places, but a company of mixed people, of proud, covetous, heady, high-minded ones, ſcoffers, and ſcorners, lyars, and ſwearers, drunkards, and all manner of ungodly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons meets in thoſe places, and all the whole body of that wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip which is maintained and practiced there, is quit another thing then what was practiced in the true Church, and ſo not the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:94006:12"/>Church of Chriſt, which is his body, which he hath Redeemed with his own blood, that he may preſent it without ſpot unto God, not having any ſpot or wrinkle or any ſuch thing.</p>
            <p>Pr. <hi>There is an opinion amongſt them, that there hath been a night of a Apoſtacy ever ſince the dayes of the Apoſtles, now the life is riſen which guided the Apostles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> There hath been a dark night of a Apoſtacy ſince the dayes of the Apoſtles, and the ſheep of the Lord they have been made a prey upon, and have been ſcattered all this cloudy dark day, not that the Lord hath not had a people through all ages even in the darkeſt times, but they have been under great ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and great tribulations, and it is alſo true that the life and ſpirit is again riſen, and the Almighty God by his power is bringing people back unto <hi>that,</hi> which the deceivers and the Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſts went <hi>from,</hi> and the foundation of many generations is raiſed up, and the Rock is witneſſed amongſt thoſe who are the reproach of many people, which ſhall daſh to pieces all that ſtrive againſt it, time will make it manifeſt.</p>
            <p>Pr. <hi>There is an opinion amongſt them, that the Scriptures are to be taken literally,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Scriptures are not of any private interpretation, neither can any man by his learning or wit underſtand, or open them, but the ſame ſpirit that was within the holy men of God which moved in them, and gave unto them an underſtanding, muſt give unto people now a knowledge and underſtanding of the Scriptures and of the things of God, and not another ſpirit.</p>
            <p>Pr. <hi>There is an opinion amongſt them, that they ought not to ſwear at all, no not when called before the civil Magiſtrate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> We have Chriſt amongſt us <hi>who is the truth,</hi> who teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth us in righteouſneſs, <hi>to let our yea, be yea, and nay, nay in all things,</hi> and we have the Scriptures of truth which teſtifie of Chriſt amongſt us, where it is plainly written in <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.33, 34, 35, 36, 37. and given forth as a command of Chriſt among many other things which he had been ſpeaking of in that ſame Chapter, ſpeaking of things in old time, which Chriſt ownes in their place, but he gives forth Lawes in a more ſtrict manner, for example, <hi>ye have heard that it was ſaid by them of old time thou ſhalt not kill, and who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever ſhall kill ſhall be in danger of the Judgement; But I ſay unto you, that whoſoever is angry with his Brother,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>ſhall be in danger of
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:94006:13"/>Judgement. Ye have heard that it was ſaid by them of old time thou ſhalt not commit adultery, but I ſay unto you that whoſoever looketh on a woman to luſt after her hath committed adultery with her already in his heart,</hi> (Mark theſe ſayings, here is mentioned, what the Law faith, and then what Chriſt ſaith, who is the perfection of all things) and ſo he goes on, and ſaith, <hi>again ye have heard that it hath been ſaid by them of old time, thou ſhalt not forſwear thy ſelf, but ſhalt perform unto the Lord thine oathes, but I ſay unto you ſwear not at all,</hi> (Mark theſe words, as he ſpoke to the perfecting of other things, ſo of this of ſwearing; he doth not ſay that it was lawful to ſwear before a Magiſtrate, as ſome ſay now, but there is nothing more plain, he puts an end to all ſwearing, not onely of vain and frivolous oathes, in common ſpeaking, but alſo all oathes whatſoever, for as he ſpoke abſolute in other things, ſo in this; for no doubt if an oath had been lawful to be taken in the Goſpel times, he would have mentioned it in this place, but it is ſo far from holding forth ſuch a thing, that it is abſolutely forbidden; <hi>the Law ſaith thou ſhalt not forſwear thy ſelf, but perform thine oathes, to the Lord, but I ſay, ſwear not at all, neither by heaven, for it is Gods Throne, nor by the earth, for it is his footstool, neither by Jeruſalem, for it is the City of the great King, neither by thy head, becauſe thou cauſt not make one hair white or black; but let your communication be yea, yea, nay, nay, for whatſoever is more then theſe cometh of evil,</hi> ſo by this it is plainly manifeſt that Chriſt hath ended all others; for as the perfection of ancient times under the Law was not to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwear, ſo the perfection of Chriſtian men is not to ſwear at all; And whereas this oppoſer, that I have to deal with, brings a Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture out of the Prophets, <hi>Jer.</hi> 4.2. and thou ſhalt ſwear <hi>the Lord liveth in truth,</hi> &amp;c. I ſay this doth not at all make void the ſayings of Chriſt becauſe he is the end of the Prophets, <hi>who ſaith ſwear not at all;</hi> and whatever other Scripture may be alleadged, it is not at all contradictory, becauſe <hi>Christ the Son is greater then Moſes, he raigns over the houſe of Jacob and Joſeph who ſwore in their day, Solomon ſwore,</hi> but <hi>a greater then Solomon is here;</hi> And whereas the Prophet ſaith thou ſhalt ſwear by the Lord, this was to bring them off from all falſe oaths, not to ſwear by <hi>Baal</hi> nor other falſe Gods; but they were in thoſe days to ſwear by the Lord; but <hi>Chriſt is come, as I have ſaid, who is the great Prophet, who ends all oathes;</hi> And whereas it is alleadged that an oath is an end of
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:94006:13"/>ſtrife, and therefore to be uſed, ſaith this oppoſer; But I ſay that whoſoever doth bring that Scripture in <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.17. to maintain ſwearing, contrary to Chriſt his command, they pervert the Scripture; for the Authour to the <hi>Hebrewes</hi> doth not ſpeak there to prove an oath lawful at that time, but he is ſpeaking of God making a promiſe to <hi>Abraham;</hi> and becauſe he could ſwear by no greater, he ſwore by himſelf, ſaying, Surely bleſſing I will bleſs thee, and multiplying I will multiply thee; and ſo after he had patiently endured, he obtained the promiſe; for men verily ſwear by the greater, and an oath for confirmation is to them an end of all ſtrife; the Apoſtle doth not bring this in oppoſition to Chriſt, but ſpeaking concerning God, who ſwore by himſelf concerning his promiſe and giving his Son, Chriſt, who ends the ſtrife; and this I further ſay, that thoſe that be in ſtrife and oathes they have not learned Chriſt; one Scripture more I ſhall add as a confirmation againſt ſwearing, and that is in <hi>Jam.</hi> 5.12 <hi>but above all things my brethren ſwear not, neither by heaven, neither by the earth, neither by any other oath</hi> (mark all oathes are forbidden) <hi>but let your yea, be yea, and your nay, nay, leaſt ye fall into condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pr. There is an opinion amongſt them, that ſinging of Pſalms is no Goſpel ordinance, eſpecially not to be uſed in mixt Aſſemblies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> This is falſe; for ſinging of Pſalms according to the Scriptures, we own, <hi>ſinging with the ſpirit and with underſtanding, making melody in our hearts to the Lord,</hi> according to thoſe Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.16. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.19. And whereas another Scripture is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadged, <hi>Jam</hi> 5.13. <hi>if any be afflicted let him pray, is any merry let him ſing Pſalms,</hi> this is owned by us, but the queſtion will be, who are they that are truly merry? I ſay that none are truly mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry but the ranſomed of the Lord, who have paſſed through many tribulations and fiery tryals, whoſe garments are waſhed with the blood of the Lamb, <hi>ſuch ſhall return to Sion with joy and ſinging, and everlaſting joy ſhall be upon their heads;</hi> But the ſongs of the wicked ſhall be turned into howling, and weeping, and ſuch we do de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and all ſuch as take <hi>Davids</hi> words (a man after Gods own heart) and turn them into Rhime, and Meeter, and a company of mixt people of proud ones, covetous, envyous, wrathful, ſcoffing and ſcornful ones, for ſuch as theſe to ſing <hi>Davids</hi> experiences, his prayers and propheſies, his weenings, waſtings, roarings, cryings,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:94006:14"/>tremblings, and ſuch like, this is a great wickedneſs, to ſpeak <hi>Davids</hi> words and ſay, <hi>O Lord I am not puft in mind, I have no ſcornful eye, I do not exerciſe my ſelf in things that be too high,</hi> &amp;c. when both Prieſt and people are proud and ſcornful; ſuch ſinging we do deny, and as ſure as God lives it ſhall be turned into howling and weeping and bitter lamentation.</p>
            <p>Pr. <hi>There is an opinion among them, that the ſpirit is the rule they ought to walk by, the ſpirit is our guide, teacher and leader.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> That which was the Rule and guide of the people of God before the Scriptures were written, and their rule and guide that writ the Scriptures, is our Rule and guide now; and that was the ſpirit of God which led and guided them in the way and truth of God, and it is written in the Prophets, <hi>all the children of the Lord ſhall be taught of the Lord;</hi> and this was the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe <hi>of Christ to ſend the Comforter, the ſpirit of truth, which ſhould lead and guide them into all truth;</hi> and this is according to the Scriptures, and ſtands over the head of all gain-ſayers, and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſers; but this is ſo plain that no reaſonable man will gainſay it; <hi>for as many as are led by the Spirit of God are the Sons of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Pr. <hi>There is an opinion amongſt them that the Trinity of perſons is a lie, and that there are not three perſons in the God head.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> What the Spirit of the Lord doth own, we own, and what is written in the Scriptures by the motion of the ſpirit we own; There is three that bear record in heaven the Father the Word, and the holy Spirit, and theſe three are <hi>One,</hi> and this we own, as for three perſons I have not read of ſuch a thing in the Scriptures, God is an incomprehenſible ſpirit, and is but One; Father Son, and Spirit, three in manifeſtation, but all one in power, one God over all, bleſſed for ever.</p>
            <p>Pr. <hi>There is an opinion amongſt them that the Miniſtry of England is Antichriſtian, and our Miniſters no Miniſters of Jeſus Christ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> 1. Such as are brought up at Schools and Colledges, and there learn <hi>Ariſtotles</hi> moral and Philoſophical Arts and ſciences, and there take certain degrees and orders, as Batchelor of Art, Maſter of Art, Batchelor of Divinity, Doctor of Divinity, and the like, and are trained up there certain years, and ſo made Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters in and by the will of man, ſuch are Antichriſtian; but ſuch are the Miniſters of <hi>England,</hi> therefore no Miniſters of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:94006:14"/>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> 2. <hi>Such as make contracts and bargains with people for certain ſet ſtipends and great ſums of money, as</hi> 80.100, 200, 300. <hi>pounds or more or leſs by the year, and will not preach without money, ſuch are Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christian, but ſuch are the Ministers of England, therefore not the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> 3. Such as denies the Doctrine of perfection, the life of pure Religion, the work and end of the Chriſtian Miniſtry, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.11.12, 13. <hi>Col.</hi> 1.27.28, 29.) and ſay that none can be perfect or free from ſin while they walk upon the earth, but muſt alwayes live in ſin, and ſin in them, ſuch a Miniſtry is Antichriſtian; But ſuch are the Miniſters of <hi>England,</hi> therefore not the Miniſters of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Pr. <hi>I would gladly know, if the Miniſters of</hi> England <hi>be not the Miniſters of Chriſt, what Miniſters are the Ministers of Christ?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> For ſatisfaction of the honeſt hearted, I ſhall declare who are the true Miniſters of Chriſt, that is to ſay, ſuch as have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived perfect gifts from God, freely, and are made Minſters by the will of God, and ſent forth by his power to turn people from darkneſs unto light; and from the power of Satan unto God, who freely Miniſter as they have freely received, who cover no mans gold, ſilver, nor apparrel, but preach the word of God freely at all times and ſeaſons as the ſpirit doth move and give utterance; and many ſuch there are amongſt thoſe that the ſcorners of this world do call <hi>Quakers,</hi> who preach the Goſpel of ſalvation freely, not ſeeking money or maintenance, and many within theſe few years in <hi>England</hi> by the power of this Miniſtry received from God, have been converted from ſin unto God.</p>
            <p>Pr. <hi>Whether Jeſus Christ have any, eſpecially deſigned for his work, or none but himſelf the Prophet of his Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Chriſt is the head of his body the Church, and is the great Prophet, and from him who is the head every member of the body receives nouriſhment and refreſhment, but I do own a Miniſtry ordained and ſent forth by him for the perfecting of the Saints, and for the edifying of the body, until we all come into the unity of the faith and of the knowledge of the Son of God unto a perfect man, even to the meaſure and ſtature and fulneſs of Chriſt as I have ſaid before,</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:94006:15"/>Pr. <hi>When the Miniſtry of</hi> England <hi>began to be Anti-christian, and how long it hath been ſo?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> The Antichriſtian powers of darkneſs hath raigned long, and I queſtion much whether ever the National Miniſtry of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> were free from Anti-chriſtianiſm, though I do believe the Lord hath had many pretious people in it, who in their time have ſtood faithful witneſſes for God, ſome have ſuffered death; but the Miniſtry was never throughly purged from popery, no not to this day, but moſt things practized are Popiſh inventions, as their Schools and Colledges where they make their Miniſters, little or nothing differing from the Papiſts Schooles and Colledges, where they make their Miniſters, their maintenance by Tythes, vicarage houſes, gleab lands, &amp;c. even as the Papiſts do; and many other things there are wherein they do agree; ſo that it is hard to tell the time when it began, but this I ſay, in the night of Apoſtacy, ſince the daies of the Apoſtles it begun.</p>
            <p>Pr. <hi>What it is that renders them Antichriſtian? taking of Tythes, or what?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Taking of Tythes is one thing that renders them ſo; but there be many other things, as their call into the Miniſtry, and being made Miniſters by the will of man, and their ſet mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, great ſumes of mony by the year, their doctrine and prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tices, ſcarce any one thing is acted or done by them in all that which they call the worſhip of God, as it was acted or done in the daies of the true Apoſtles; and if it were ſo that they were found in the very practice of the Apoſtles, yet not being led by the ſame ſpirit, it is antichriſtian: for the Chriſtian worſhip was in the ſpirit and in the truth; and all peoples &amp; nations, though they may have all the words given forth from the ſpirit, if they be not <hi>in</hi> the ſpirit and <hi>in</hi> the truth, they be falſe worſhipers, and are Antichriſtian, that profeſſe Chriſt in words, but have not the life of Chriſt within them; more I might ſay as to theſe things, but ſo much having been written already by others, I ſhall proceed further; only I take notice of three accuſations againſt us, that is, 1. That we deny the Trinity of perſons; 2. The Divine au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the Scriptures. 3 And the Souls immortality; to the two firſt I have already ſpoken; and the Soul we ſay is immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal, and ſo I leave the lyar to receive his portion in the lake of end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe miſery, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.8.</p>
            <p>Now I come to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> particulars wherein this oppoſer goes about
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:94006:15"/>to caſt an odium upon the <hi>Quakers</hi> bringing ſeveral things which he ſaith the Jeſuites and Papiſts holds; it ſeems he is well acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with them, but what is that to the matter; becauſe the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil believes there is a God, ſhall not I believe truth becauſe the Devils believes? If Jeſuites an I Papiſts, Turks and Infidels hold any truth, their holding of it ſhall not make me deny it; but truth I ſhall own where ever I finde it, and all Lyers and falſe accuſers, and that which is contrary to truth I deny; but I ſhall come to the particulars, and what concerns thoſe whom he calls <hi>Quakers</hi> I ſhall ſpeak to, and what concernes the Jeſuites and Papiſts, let them anſwer for themſelves, if they will.</p>
            <p>Pr. <hi>Jeſuites have low, baſe and vile thoughts of the Scripture, its with them a noſe of Wax, a dead letter, no ſufficient ground of Faith nor judge of controverſies, ſo</hi> Bellarmine, <hi>&amp;c. ſo</hi> Quakers.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> That the <hi>Quakers</hi> have low, baſe and vile thoughts of the Scriptures is very falſe, and wickedneſſe it is to ſay ſo; for we dearly own and highly prize the Scriptures, and own them to be a true teſtimony of him who is the author and foundation of faith, Chriſt Jeſus; but life is not to be found in the Scripture, but in Chriſt, who is the life and the quickning ſpirit, who is the judge of all controverſies according to the Scriptures.</p>
            <p>Pr. <hi>Jeſuites and Papists cries up ſalvation by the light and law of nature, without the knowledge of Chriſt, &amp;c. ſo Quakers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> We ſay as I have ſaid before, ſalvation is by Chriſt who is the light of the world, and lighteth every man that commeth into the world, and not by the light and law of nature without the knowledge of Chriſt, this charge is altogether falſe, as to the <hi>Quakers;</hi> as for the other let them anſwer for themſelves.</p>
            <p>Pr. <hi>Papists ſay the Church of England is no true Church. They ſay the Miniſtry of</hi> England <hi>is antichristian, and ſo Quakers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> To both theſe I have ſpoken of before, to which I refer the Reader.</p>
            <p>Pr. <hi>Subeſse Romano pontifici eſt de neceſſitate ſalutis; No ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation for us unleſſe we become Catholicks in their ſence. Quakers ſay we are all damned except we turn Quakers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> We ſay this, and it is no more then truth, that except ye repent and be converted, ye muſt all periſh; But as for the words as they are laid down, they proceed from the wickedneſſe of his evil heart, and are not true; our way is Chriſt, and this is the way of holineſſe, and is but one, and there is none other, and to
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:94006:16"/>this way muſt all come that are ſaved, and muſt know trembling and quaking before all wickedneſſe be thrown down, and truth and righteouſneſſe be ſet up; therefore let none deſpiſe the power of God, leaſt ye be cut of in his feirce wrath.</p>
            <p>Pr. <hi>Jeſuits allow women to do the worke of the Ministry, &amp;c. Quakers allow womens preaching as ſpiritual.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> God hath ſpoken by his holy prophet, ſaying, it ſhall come to paſſe in the latter daies, that I will pour forth of my ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit upon my Sons and daughters, upon my ſervants and hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maids; and where the ſpirit of God is, there is liberty, it is not to be quenched, neither in Son nor daughter; where the ſeed is witneſſed either in male or female, to wit, Chriſt who is one in the female as well as in the male, and where he rules and reignes he may and ought to ſpeak, and this is according to Scriptures, but let the woman be ſilent as ſaith the Scripture.</p>
            <p>Pr. <hi>Papiſts look upon miracles as ſignes of the true Church, ſo Quakers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> This is but the mans imagination, becauſe he would have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ething to ſay, as for miracles I do not look for them, but if any by the power and ſpirit of God do work miracles, as ſome have done among us, we do own it, and give God the honour, whoſe work and power it is, and not any work of the creature.</p>
            <p>Pr. <hi>Papists put a high esteem on viſions and Revelations e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qualling them with, or preferring them above the written Word; ſo Quakers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> True viſions and true Revelations ſeen and revealed by the true ſpirit I muſt needs own, if a Turk or infidel ſhould pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe the truth, its no worſe for their profeſſing of it; And ſo I ſay that which is revealed by the ſame ſpirit which was within them that gave forth the Scripture, is one and the ſame with the Scriptreu, for the Truth is the ſame yeſterday, to day and for ever.</p>
            <p>Pr. <hi>The Jeſuites ſay a man may be ſaved if he will, if he will follow the light, &amp;c. and the Quakers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> I have formerly anſwered to this point, yet this further; I ſay the ſaving power is not in mans will, but in Chriſt the light, and whoſoever believes in and followes the light ſhall be ſaved, and he that believes not, but followes his own will ſhall be damned.</p>
            <p>Pr. <hi>The Papists extenuate imputed Righteouſneſse in ſetting up their own Inherent Righteeuſneſse, ſo Quakers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:94006:16"/>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> All our own Righteouſneſſe is as filthy rags, and we do not ſet it up but deny it, together with all unrighteouſneſſe; but we exalt and ſet up Chriſt, who of God is made unto us Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, Juſtification, Redemption, and all other things who dwels in us and is our life, and we in him, and have our peace.</p>
            <p>Pr. <hi>Papiſts ſay they can keep all Gods commandements perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, fulfill the law in their own perſons, ſo</hi> Bell, <hi>and the Quakers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Through the ſtrength and power of Chriſt, that dwels in us we can do all things, and his commandements are not grievous but joyous to us; and Chriſt doth fulfill the Righteouſneſſe of the Law <hi>in us, who walk<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not after the fleſh but after the ſpirit, and whoſoever ſaith he knowes God and keeps not his commandents, is a ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar and the truth is not in him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Pr. <hi>The Church Papists hold that their Church is infallible, which at last is the Pope; ſo Quakers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> We do not hold the <hi>Pope</hi> to be the Church, neither do we believe the Pope to be infallible, any more then the Prieſts and Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Pr. <hi>Jeſuits ſay there is no foundation for Inſants Baptiſm in the written word.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Pr. <hi>The Jeſuites ſay baptiſm is of mans institution; ſo Quakers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> We are bold to affirme it, and ſay there is no command nor example nor practice in the Scripture for Infants baptiſm, it is an invention of man, and I lay it upon all the Prieſts of <hi>England,</hi> and Papiſts, and all who practice it, to bring me a proof of it from the Scriptures, or elſe confeſſe their ſin in doing that which was never commanded, nor by any of the Miniſters of Chriſt practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</p>
            <p>Pr. <hi>Jeſuites make their Pope a</hi> God, &amp;c. Quakers <hi>make themſelves Gods, curſe men, damn them to Hell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> It ſeemes this Prieſt is wholly given up to the Devil, in venting forth ſo many and groſſe wicked lyes; we do not make our ſelves Gods but denie our ſelves, and take up the Croſſe and and follow Chriſt; But we do witneſſe that God dwels in us; and we never curſe men nor damn them to Hell; but we teſtifie againſt ſin, which if not forſaken and repented of, will lead men to Hell; for the wages of ſin is death.</p>
            <p>Pr. <hi>Jeſuites call us heriticks, dogs, &amp;c. and the</hi> Quakers <hi>calls us the brood of</hi> Cain, Baals <hi>Priests falſe prophets, Seducers, &amp;c</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:94006:17"/>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> They that are envious and wrathful are of <hi>Cains</hi> genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and off ſpring, and if we find any of the prieſts of <hi>England</hi> in that nature, we muſt tell them the truth, it is no other language then what the ſpirit of the Lord hath given to deceivers and falſe prophets in times paſt, and the prieſts of <hi>England</hi> being found in the ſame ſteps and covetous practices, we do them no wrong to give them their right names.</p>
            <p>Pr. <hi>Papists place most in external obſervations, ſeeming autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, ſo Quakers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> The lyar will arive at Hell at laſt, when he hath filled up his meaſure: once more I teſtifie that we do not place moſt in outward things, but in Chriſt is our ſtrength who works in us to will and to do of his good pleaſure.</p>
            <p>Pr. <hi>Papists prefer</hi> Jeromes <hi>verſion of the Bible before the</hi> Hebrew <hi>and the</hi> Greek, <hi>ſo</hi> Fox <hi>and others deny</hi> Greek <hi>and</hi> Hebrew <hi>to be the original, preferring the Engliſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Where did ever this oppoſer hear <hi>Fox</hi> and others ſpeak of preferring the <hi>Engliſh</hi> before the <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Hebrew,</hi> the <hi>Engliſh</hi> we own in its place and ſo <hi>Hebrew</hi> and <hi>Greek;</hi> but not any of theſe Languages can open the myſteries of God, therefore let all fleſh be ſilent before the Lord, and let God alone be exalted.</p>
            <p>Pr. <hi>The Jeſuits cast off prayer to God, and pray to Saints, &amp;c. Quakers have cast off prayer to God, when do they pray in their fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, meetings? &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re is a Charge and a queſtion laid down: the charge is that <hi>Quakers</hi> have left off praying to God. Now if the <hi>Quakers</hi> have not left off prayer to God, then <hi>Ia. Liveſey</hi> is a lyar; but they have not left off prayer to God, as thouſands in this Nation can teſtifie, but pray often both in their meetings and in their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies as the ſpirit of God doth move and guide them, therefore is <hi>Liveſey</hi> a lyar.</p>
            <p>Pr. <hi>The Jeſuites ſay that the Empire of learning is within the heritage of the Jeſuits, ſo Quakers ſay we are in darkneſſe, all our eyes are out, theirs onely open.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Every tree is known by his fruits, &amp; ſo we ſay of the Prieſts of <hi>England</hi> after all their talking and profeſſion, and having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived ſo much mony, ſee what may, be reaped in their fields, even a great Crop of corruption pride and covetouſneſſe reigning in themſelves, and what can be expected to be brought forth in peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:94006:17"/>but like Prieſt, like people, wandring aſtray like ſheep with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a ſhepherd; but the day of the Lord is dawned, and the Lord hath opened our eyes, praiſes to his holy Nime; and we deſire that their eyes may be opened, that they might ſee their filthineſs, and repent that their ſouls might live.</p>
            <p>Thus I have gone through his 20. particulars, and what is truth I have owned, and what is not I have denyed, and turned it back again into the old bottle from whence it ſprung: I ſhall haſten to an end, for it is out of my life to wade in ſuch muddy filthy ſtuff as this is, onely for Truths ſake to remove the ſtumbling block out of the way of the ſimple: And now whoſoever thou art that reads this, let not prejudice enter into thee, but in the feare of God weigh and try things, and hold faſt that which is good.</p>
            <p>The next thing I meet with is ſome queſtions, which he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounds, and then goes about to anſwer, or give his cenſure; I may ſpeak ſomthing to the queſtions, and to other things as the Lord moves.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>What may we rationally and Charitably conceive or judge of the Quakers pretended piety and ſanctity, have the truth of grace in them or no?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Wicked ungodly men, ſuch as I have found this Prieſt, a Lyar, a Blaſphemer, a falſe accuſer have nothing to do to judge of the Piety and Sanctity of the people of God; but they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves are reſerved for the judgement of the great day, when the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ord Jeſus ſhal be revealed from heaven with his mighty Angels in flaming fire, taking vengeance on them that know not God, &amp; that obey not the Goſpel of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt who ſhall be puniſhed with evelaſting deſtruction from the preſence of the Lord, and from the glory of his power, when he ſhall come to be glorified in his Saints, and to be admired <hi>in</hi> all them that believe; this day is comming on apace, wherein the deceits of all deceivers ſhall be made manifeſt; and this know, that our Piety and Sanctity is not pretended, but true and firm, proceeding from the true root and ſure foundation, and we have the truth of grace in us, by which we are taught to deny the deceitful Miniſtry of Antichriſt, and all ungodly luſts and pleaſures, and to live a godly and ſober life in this preſent World.</p>
            <p>Some things I take notice of in this oppoſers pretended an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:94006:18"/>to this firſt queſtion which he chargeth upon the <hi>Quakers,</hi> which juſtly falls upon his own head, falſe doctrine ſaith he begets falſe Piety, now what can be falſer doctrine then to deny perfection and cleanſing from ſin? this opens a door to wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and ſtrikes at the life of Religion, denying the very end of Chriſt his comming and being manifeſted, which is to deſtroy the works of the Devil; ſo this is the ground of the bad converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and falſ piety, and whereas he ſeems to ſtrike at the converfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and practiſes of thoſe called <hi>Quakers,</hi> I leave it to all ſober people to judge whether the <hi>Quakers</hi> or the Prieſts walkes more ſtrictly and ſoberly, and which of them deny themſelves the moſt; for thoſe who are found moſt in ſolf-denial, are the loweſt diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Chriſt, and whereas he queries how can a good life and an ill belief ſtand together, corrupt head &amp; corrupt heart commonly go together, corrupt principles breeds and ſeeds corrupt practicer, all theſe conſidered, they fall heavy upon the Prieſts and carnal profeſſors, for how can there be any worſe belief, then to believe that people ſhall never be pure nor clean, nor overcome ſin while they live, this is the ill belief, from whence all the corrupt practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces have liberty; but we own no ſuch faith, but our faith is the giſt of God, which purifies our hearts, and gives us victory over the World &amp; the luſts of it; and ſo a good belief and a good life ſtands firme and faſt together; and whereas he ſpeakes of the power of Goddlineſſe, and the powen of ſin cannot dwell together; I ſay that the Prieſts of <hi>England</hi> are ſo fur from the power of godlineſſe, that few are come ſo far as the forme of godlineſſe, but are ſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding their time like dreamers, keeping people in the dark; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies learning, but never able to come to the knowledge of God.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Qu. <hi>What is the Religion of the Quakers?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Our Religion is not known to the World, nor ever can be learned by a wordly principle, but the ſum of it is this to love God, with all our hearts, and our neighbours as our ſelves, to viſit the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therleſs &amp; the widdows in their afflictions, and to keep our ſelves unſpotted from the World; and whoſoever ſhall learn our Religion, which is the one true religion, muſt own that principle of <hi>light</hi> which is of Chriſt, which ſhines in the conſcienoe, and ſtands as a witneſs againſt all ſin and evil, and leads out of the Worlds Luſts, and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, into holineſs and Righteouſneſſe, which exerciſes the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience towards God and man, and leads in the way of Juſtice,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:94006:18"/>and Righteouſneſs; for our Religion doth not admit of any ſin or iniquity whatſoever; but is holy and pure, by which we are joyned to God, and have unity with him, and worſhip him in ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and truth.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Qu. Is it your duty to indeavour the conviction of them?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> We are convinced long ago of the evil of the <hi>Prieſts</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> and of the deadneſs and emptineſs of their forms, and dead obſervations, and the Lord hath turned us from them, and have converted us from evil unto good, and we are his, and in vain it is for all the <hi>Prieſts</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> with all their cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning craft, to convict, or draw us back again; no, no, we are drawn by the cords of everlaſting love, out of that thick mire and Clay, which they and thouſands of their hearers ſtick faſt in; and it is our deſires, and alſo our endeavours to draw them out of it, that they may feed with us at the Lords Table, and eat plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully to the ſatisfying of their hungry ſouls. And whereas he ſpeaks of prayer to God for us; alas poor man, his prayers we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny; God hath no regard to him and his prayers, they are abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, becauſe of his great wickedneſs; Therefore before he talk of praying for others, let him repent of his ſin, left God cut him down and caſt him off for ever.</p>
            <p>Furthermore this oppoſer vomits up more of his filthyneſs and wickednes, ſaying, now they caſt by the written word, ſaying ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is attaineable without Chriſt. Oh! horrible wicked lyar, Gods vengeance hangs over his head; Scriptures we own, and Chriſt alone our ſalvation: Further he goes on and ſaies <hi>Quakers</hi> are hereticks, therefore are to be rejected and left to the civil Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates Cognizance.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> By this I ſmell his wicked ſpirit, no leſſe then blood would ſatisfie that ſpirit; but the Lord hath put a curb in their mouthes; thats the ſpirit of an heretick that would puniſh the bodies of people; and not the ſpirit of the true Apoſtles, for <hi>they</hi> wreſtled not againſt fleſh and blood but againſt principalities and powers, againſt ſpiritual wickedneſs in high places; but I ſhal paſs by ſome of his chaffy ſtuff, and leave it to be blowne away by the breath of the Almighty, and ſo come to the next.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Qu. Whether are Quakers witches?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> I anſwer no; but the Lord hath raiſed them up by the power of his ſpirit to teſtifie againſt all the ſorceries, and witch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crafts and inchantments which are found amongſt the Merchants
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:94006:19"/>of <hi>Babylon,</hi> the black prieſts, who have been clouded with blackneſs who have long beguiled unſtable ſouls, and made Merchandize of them; ſuch as led people from the Spirit of God, were witches, and bewitched the <hi>Galatians,</hi> and ſuch now in <hi>England,</hi> who draw people from the light, life and ſpirit within to carnal ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervances without, ſuch are they that bewitch and beguil poor ſouls; Now whereas this oppoſer doth bring ſome Scriptures, whereby his intent is to prove the <hi>Quakers</hi> witches, but I ſhall examine them; the ſpirit of God (ſaith he) ſets out impoſtors to the life, ſometimes comparing them to deceitful Merchants who can ſet a fair gloſſe upon their falſe ware; to which I ſay, who are more deceitful then thoſe Merchants of <hi>Babylon,</hi> the covetous Teachers, who heapes a great deal of fluff together, nay ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time ſteal a Scrmon, and ſet a fair gloſſe on it and ſell it to the people, and when they have ſold it once over, and received money for it, yet they oftentimes ſell it over, and over again, and ſo cheats and cozens the people; then he alleadges, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.3. they are ſaid with fained words to make Merchandize of ſouls; here he hath learned of his maſter the Devil to leave out part of the Scripture; the Apoſtle ſaith thus; <hi>and through covetouſneſs ſhall they with feigned words make Merchandize of you,</hi> this hits the pricſts and ſtrikes very near them; and the Apoſtle further marks them out, <hi>ſpots they are and blemiſhes, ſporting themſelves with their own deceivings having eyes full of Adultery, and that cannot ceaſe from ſin, begniling unſtable ſouls, an heart they have exerciſed with covetous practices;</hi> whether this toucheth the prieſts of <hi>Eng.</hi> or the <hi>Quakers,</hi> I leave it to the wiſe in heart to judge, Another Scripture alleadged 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.2.17 <hi>for we are not as many which corrupt the word of God, but as of ſincerity, but as of God in the ſight of God ſpeak we in Chriſt;</hi> now how can thoſe ſpeak in Chriſt, that denyes Chriſt in them, and oppoſe his light within as the pariſh prieſts do, and ſo are not like the Apoſtles; Another Scripture I find quoted <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.14. <hi>that we hencefotrh be no more children toſsed to and fro with every wind of Doctrine by the ſlight of men and cunning craftineſs whereby they lay in wait to deceive;</hi> But thoſe called <hi>Quakers</hi> do not go about to draw people from God, but to bring home to him, that they may be preſented perfect in Chriſt Jeſus, as in the 13. verſe of the ſaid fourth Chapter which the prieſts of <hi>England</hi> deny, and ſayes none can be perfect in this life, and ſo deceive your ſouls by their ſlights and cunning craftinſs.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:94006:19"/>Another Scripture alleadged by this oppoſer is, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.8.9. but read from the beginning of the Chapter, and there as in a glaſs thou maiſt read the Character of the pariſh Prieſts of <hi>England,</hi> read the Chapter thorow, and then try and let the light of Jeſus Chriſt in thy conſcience Judge, without partiality; Another Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture is in <hi>Jude</hi> the 11. the words are theſe, <hi>woe unto them, for they have gone in the way of</hi> Cain, <hi>and run greedily after the error of</hi> Balaam <hi>for reward, and periſhed in the gain-ſaying of</hi> Core; theſe are the ſeveral Scriptures which the adverſary brings to prove the <hi>Quakers</hi> to be witches; but to thoſe whoſe eyes are in any meaſure opened, there are not many ſuch Scriptures that ſo nearly touchea the covetous prieſts and deceitful Merchants of <hi>England,</hi> but their folly ſhall be made manifeſt to all in Gods day of light; ſome other frothy things are ſpoken of by this adverſary, as tying of Ribbands or Bracelets about mens wreſts; oh horrible deceiti! I am ſure few people in all <hi>England</hi> do ſlight and caſt off ſuch bables more then we do; and as for his ſpeaking of falling into trances, ſrantick poſtures, grovelling on the ground; ſoaming at the mouth, and ſuch like frothy ſtuff, all this doth ariſe as ſmoke out of the bottomleſs pit, which God will blaſt, and hath already blaſted; for the Lord hath opened the eyes of thouſands in this Nation to ſee the envy and wickedneſs of thoſe who have invented ſuch wicked lies againſt the people of God; and they ſee and have found them lyars, and God is cauſing the light to ſhine forth, and the beauty of his people begins to appear, which hath long been marred and ſtained by reproachfull lying, and backbiting tongues.</p>
            <p>Queſt. 5. <hi>Whether are the</hi> Quakers <hi>to be tolerated, ſuffered, or to be puniſhed by the civil Magiſtrate?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> If the Prieſts might be judges, they would ſoon have their hands in blood, though little cauſe there is for it, but one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly their trade is like to go down, and therefore if theſe men be ſuffered their <hi>Diana</hi> will fall, they are nearly related to their brethren the Prieſts in the dayes of Chriſt who cryed out, crucifie him, crucifie him, though <hi>Pilate</hi> a Magiſtrate ſound no fault in him, and as it was then, ſo it is now, the ſervant is not greater then his Lord, we cannot expect better things from this wicked generation, but ſufferings and reproaches, ſtocks and impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but the Lord is our ſupport, and we magnifie his name that we are of that number who are counted worthy to ſuffer for his<gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:94006:20"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:94006:20"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
